בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is קנ, Kuf Nun, 150,
and we pick up with on קנ, Kuf Nun, and what we're
dealing with is a line in the משנה Mishnah that says that
the line between a מתנת שכיב מרע Matnat Shechiv Mera when it
has that special status that it reverts if he gets better and
does not require קניין kinyan
and a normal מתנה matanah is whether it's all the property or
only some of it. And the משנה Mishnah said that the difference
between all and some is דשייר קרקע כל שהוא, di-shiyar karka kol
shehu, a little bit of land. And then the גמרא Gemara though
says a statement in the name of רב יהודה אמר רב Rav
Yehuda Amar Rav and a statement of רב ירמיה בר אבא Rav
Yirmeyah bar Abba that קרקע karka doesn't mean קרקע, karka, land doesn't
mean land, the little doesn't mean a little,
so it doesn't have to be land, it has to be any
amount of property, any amount of money or not land
property but property in general, land or otherwise, that is enough to
support him even is enough to support him,
he's leaving over enough to provide for his support. And if that's
the case, then we assume that he's understanding that even if he
gets better what he gave away was given away because he's retaining
for himself enough to provide him with ongoing support. So that was
the claim. But the גמרא Gemara challenged it and it said how
could you say that קרקע karka doesn't mean קרקע karka and how
could you say that כל שהוא, kol shehu, the smallest amount, doesn't
mean כל שהוא? kol shehu? So yesterday we saw that it brought
evidence in a case where in a משנה Mishnah it said קרקע,
karka, that even like a case about an עבד, eved, and if
you free a slave and if you said you left over some
קרקע karka or even if you're saying you're leaving over some מטלטלין,
metaltelin, and it says there we say that קרקע karka doesn't mean
קרקע, karka, but the גמרא Gemara says yeah, but that's because it
was a context of קרקע, karka, so it explains how in one
example we were being imprecise because the larger context was קרקע. karka.
But if there was not a case where the larger context was
קרקע, karka, the משנה Mishnah would not have said קרקע karka if
it did not mean קרקע. karka. Okay, so that's a challenge to
the idea that the language that the word קרקע karka is not
really precise. Now we're going to challenge, now we're going to look
at this claim that the word כל שהוא kol shehu is not
precise. So let's take a look now as we continue on קנ
Kuf Nun and the גמרא Gemara says like this,
there's a little ב Bet in a half parenthesis at the beginning
of a line, it is about 10 lines down and it says
the following: וכל היכא דתני כל שהוא לית ליה שיעורא? v'chol heicha
d'tani kol shehu leit lei shiura? Do you want to claim so
your challenge to the argument that כל שהוא kol shehu is imprecise
is that it says כל שהוא, kol shehu, כל שהוא kol shehu
should be taken literally? So the pushback is no, I'll show you
that's not true. It's not that every time we say the word
כל שהוא kol shehu we mean even the smallest amount. I'll show
you a place where it doesn't mean literal. ותנן, V'hatnan, we taught
in a משנה: Mishnah: רבי דוסא בן הורכינס אומר חמש רחלות גזוזות
מנה מנה ופרס חייבות בראשית הגז, Rabbi Dosa ben Harkinas omer: Chamesh
rachelot gzezot maneh maneh u'pras chayavot b'reshit hagez,
that you know only when you do your first shearings of the
sheep you have to give a gift to the כהן. kohen. So
is there a minimum amount? So
רבי דוסא בן הורכינס Rabbi Dosa ben Harkinas says first of all
it has to be the shearing of five sheep, anything fewer than
five sheep would not be obligated, number one. Number two, each sheep
has to provide
a מנה ופרס, maneh u'pras, that's a weight of wool, and only
when you have that full amount are you obligated to give part
of that shearing to the כהן. kohen. וחכמים אומרים, V'Chachamim omrim, but
the sages stay, חמש רחלות גזוזות, chamesh rachelot gzezot, yes
we agree it has to be five sheep, but כל שהוא, kol
shehu, even if each sheep only provided a smallest amount. So there
it says כל שהוא, kol shehu, and I'm going to show you
it's not literal. Why? ואמרינן, V'amrinan, and we say: וכמה כל שהוא?
v'kama kol shehu? How much is a small amount, how much is
the smallest possible amount? אמר רב מנה ופרס, Amar Rav: maneh u'pras,
the same thing of מנה ופרס, maneh u'pras, but it's not per
sheep, it's total. So a total of מנה ופרס, maneh u'pras, ובלבד
שיהיו מחומשות, u'bilvad she-yehu muchamashot,
and each one, it can't be that one sheep provides 90 percent
and the other 10 percent, each sheep has to provide a fifth
of that, of that one and a half. Okay, so whatever that
is, that's I guess each one has to provide three tenths of
a מנה. maneh. All right, so anyways rather than really being a
כל שהוא, kol shehu, what we actually say the word כל שהוא
kol shehu means is three tenths of a מנה. maneh. So you
see that כל שהוא kol shehu does not mean כל שהוא, kol
shehu, so don't give me a hard time that I'm saying that
כל שהוא kol shehu in our משנה Mishnah does not mean כל
שהוא. kol shehu. So the גמרא Gemara says no, same point as
before. התם בדין הוא דלא ליתני כל שהוא. Hatam bedin hu d'lo
litni kol shehu. You're right, it should not have said כל שהוא,
kol shehu, it should have said you know three tenths of a
מנה maneh per sheep. ואיידי דקאמר תנא קמא שיעורא רבא, V'aidi d'ka'amar
tanna kamma shiura rabba, and since the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said
a large measure, מנה ופרס, maneh u'pras, one and a half
מנה, maneh, אמר איהו נמי שיעורא זוטרא, amar ee hu nami shiura
zutra, and he's saying something that's very small in comparison, then versus
your one and a half this person is saying three tenths of
a מנה, maneh, קרי ליה כל שהוא. kari lei kol shehu. It's
saying no, even the smallest amount. But
it's saying smallest amount because it's responding to a very large amount.
So there it's לאו דווקא lav davka smallest, it means a tiny
amount. There is a minimum, the minimum is three tenths, but it
can call it a כל שהוא kol shehu because it's responding to
this very large amount. But again in our משנה... Mishnah... Our משנה
mishnah has no context. Our משנה mishnah is not responding, it's not
in the context of talking about land. It's not responding to a
claim that says that it has to be a large amount. Our
משנה mishnah is just saying in a vacuum and by itself that
if you leave over a little bit, it's considered a not a
מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shechiv mera and the definition of a little
bit is the smallest amount of land. So in that context, don't
tell me that land doesn't mean land and the smallest amount doesn't
mean a smallest amount. Okay, those words clearly are not in any
larger context and are not responding to anything, so they clearly have
to be taken literally, which is a pretty darn good argument. Okay.
So that's the pushback that we really do mean קרקע כל שהוא.
karka kol shehu. All right. So now the גמרא gemara continues. פשיטא,
pishita, now, it's obvious. אמר: amar: מטלטלי לפלניא, metaltale l'planya, if somebody
says, now this is not necessarily a שכיב מרע shechiv mera although
easily could be, but the רשב"ם rashbam says this also includes a
case that somebody is doing a קנין, kinyan, like I just go
ahead and say, David, here, give me your handkerchief and in exchange
for me taking your handkerchief, I am transferring all of my מטלטלין
metaltelin to Gloria, all of my cattle to Gloria. What's included in
that word מטלטלין? metaltelin? So either I do it as a קנין
kinyan in a healthy person or שכיב מרע shechiv mera says it:
all of my מטלטלין metaltelin to Dov. What is included in that
word מטלטלין? metaltelin? So מטלטלי לפלניא: metaltale l'planya: מאני תשמישתי קני, manei
tashmishtei kani, so you get all sort of the, you know, all
of like the objects that are, I don't even know how to
translate מאני תשמישתי, manei tashmishtei, all sort of, you know, implements of...
such a bad translation.
Does it mean linens and cloth items for the home?
No, מאני תשמישתי manei tashmishtei is basically everything, anything you use. All
his stuff, thank you. All things
he uses,
לבר מחטי ושערי, levar mechiti u'se'arei, the one thing, so מטלטלין metaltelin
that would not include is food, is, you know, wheat and barley
and presumably other food as well. Even though technically it is מטלטלין
metaltelin from a הלכה halacha point of view, anything that's not land
is מטלטלין, metaltelin, but from the way people talk, when they say
מטלטלין, metaltelin, they're not thinking about their food. Okay, they're thinking about
durable objects. Okay, so basically, it's all types of like durable objects,
but not foodstuff. The רשב"ם rashbam adds, the רשב"ם rashbam says that
it's also not meant to include livestock, okay, or I presumably pets
either, okay. So animals and food, even though technically speaking are מטלטלין
metaltelin legally, that's not what a person means when they say מטלטלין.
metaltelin.
Is this a primary figure that explores the definition of מטלטלין? metaltelin?
No, this explores the definition of מטלטלין metaltelin in לשון בני אדם
lashon bnei adam when, okay, in the legal meaning, includes everything that's
not land. Okay, כל kol now says: כל מטלטלי לפלניא, kol metaltale
l'planya, all of my מטלטלין. metaltelin.
So somehow all doesn't just mean everything that's normally in the category,
the extra word all is coming to say a broader definition of
מטלטלין. metaltelin. אפילו חטי ושערי, afilu chiti u'se'arei, even wheat and even,
you know, yeah, wheat and barley,
presumably also even livestock. ואפילו ריחיים העליונה, v'afilu rechayim ha'elyona, even the
upper millstone, even though it's huge, right, and, you know, technically it's
movable, it's not nailed down, but you would normally not think of
it as מטלטלין metaltelin because you don't normally move it from place
to place. קנה, kana, you would be קונה. koneh. לבר מריחיים התחתונה.
levar me'rechayim ha'tachtona. The one thing you don't is the lower millstone,
because that also is not nailed down, the difference is that the
top one you would sometimes transport, like if you needed to get
it fixed or, you know, I don't know, smoothed or whatever it
might be. So there would be every now and then you would
transport it, whereas the bottom one you would never move.
So the top one actually moves.
The top one moves, that's a good point, it moves in the
use. It doesn't move to a different place, but it moves in
its place. Right. As opposed to something that might not be nailed
down but would like never be moved. Like I don't know, what
do you think about those bookcases? Would you call them מטלטלין? metaltelin?
All you have to do is empty them and move them, right?
But like when would it be that you would do it, right?
So anyway, so that's the question here.
Okay. So even if you said כל מטלטלי, kol metaltale, the one
thing you exclude is the bottom millstone. כל דמיטלטל, kol d'mitaltel, let's
say you used it not as a noun but as an adjective,
anything that is movable has the quality of being able to be
moved. Okay, אפילו ריחיים התחתונה קנה, afilu rechayim ha'tachtona kana, that even
the bottom one, because the bottom one is theoretically movable. Okay. I'm
wondering about what would it include, that classic example in the גמרא
gemara about an עציץ נקוב? atzitz nakuv? An עציץ נקוב, atzitz nakuv,
right, is like a flowerpot with a hole in it that's sitting
on the ground. Technically it's קרקע karka because it's dirt and it's
connected to dirt, right, it's like a little mound on the ground
surrounded by a flowerpot, but it's also movable. Right? So legally it's
קרקע, karka, but maybe in a לשון בני אדם, lashon bnei adam,
I mean, you could imagine I got a lot of plants in
the house, right? I mean, are they considered מטלטלין metaltelin when I
say מטלטלין, metaltelin, right? It could be that it even, you know,
it even goes into the realm of what's considered קרקע.
karka. Just because it's the first מסכת Masechet it hasn't referenced it,
so you had to bring it up.
Exactly. Okay, איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu, they asked the following question: עבדא,
avda, let's regarding slaves, that's an example where also legally they're קרקע,
karka, but what do people refer to them as? Okay, are they
included in a person's term when a person refers to מטלטלין? metaltelin?
Because slaves do move around, even on their own
accord. Okay, כמקרקעי או כמטלטלי דמי. kemakarkei o kemetalteli dami. Now, the
רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafot both underscore that from a legal perspective
they're קרקע, karka, okay? So, you know, the way שקונה shekoneh them
is similar to קרקע, karka, they're excluded from a lot of הלכות,
halachot, like, you know, ריבית ribis and גזל, gezel, etc., like קרקע
karka is excluded. Legally they are קרקע karka or they're like קרקע,
karka, but in the way people refer to them, are they included
in the term מטלטלין? metaltelin? Now, by the way, it's possible as
we saw before and I guess as we're going to see that
people could refer to it as both, meaning it could be that
if I say all my מטלטלין, metaltelin, I include my slaves. It
could also be and if I say all my קרקע, karka, I
include my slaves, right? Not necessarily mutually exclusive categories, right? Legally they
are, but you know in the way people refer to them it
could be they refer to them both ways. But will it be
included in the term מטלטלין? metaltelin? Okay. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה
דרב אביא לרב אשי, amar leh Rav Acha breih de-Rav Avia le-Rav
Ashi, תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. המוכר את העיר, hamocher
et ha-ir, ah, we're reminding us of some previous פרקים prakim in
בבא בתרא. Bava Batra. Okay. המוכר את העיר, hamocher et ha-ir, somebody
sells a town. מכר בתים שיחין ומערות, machar batim shichin u-mearot, they
sell the, you know, the houses, the cisterns, the, whatever, the other,
the wells, ומרחצאות, u-merchatzaut, the bathhouses, ובית הבדין, u-veit ha-badin, the pressing
houses for olives, ובית השלחין, u-veit ha-shlachin, and the irrigation canals. אבל
לא את המטלטלין. aval lo et ha-metaltelin. So basically anything that is
attached and part of the ground, but nothing that is מטלטלין metaltelin
that is movable. ובזמן שאמר היא וכל מה שבתוכה, u-v'zman she-amar hi
v'chol mah she-betochah, but if he says I'm not just selling the
town, I'm selling all of its contents, right? It's like are you
selling a house, furnished or unfurnished? With its contents or without? So
if you're selling it with its contents, in that case,
אפילו היו בה בהמה או עבדים הרי כולם מכורין. afilu hayu bah
behemah o avadim harei kulam mechurin. Even animals and slaves, everything, you
know, everything is sold, all of its contents. So it sounds like
that fundamentally בהמה ועבדים behemah va-avadim are in the מטלטלין metaltelin column,
right? Now, look, it is a little funny. You didn't say the
word קרקע karka and you didn't say the word מטלטלין, metaltelin, right?
So it's not the world's greatest proof, right? It could say that
when you think about a town, do you put them, you know,
which side of the line do you put them in without other
specifications? It doesn't prove that when you say the word מטלטלין metaltelin
that you think that slaves are included in מטלטלין, metaltelin, right? So
it's not exactly a proof. Anyway, but let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. אי
אמרת בשלמא כמטלטלי דמי, ei amart bishlama kemetalteli dami, if you think
normally they're in the מטלטלין metaltelin category and this would be only
in the מטלטלין metaltelin category, not in the קרקע karka category. ומשום
הכי לא מזדבני ברישא. u-mishum hachi lo mizdabni be-reisha. Therefore when you're
selling the town, even though you're selling all things that are, that
are land and connected to land, you're not selling slaves. אלא אי
אמרת כמקרקעי דמי, ela ei amart kemakarkei dami, if you normally put
them in the land category, so אמאי לא מזדבני, amai lo mizdabni,
why didn't it sell when you initially just said the town? So,
so the גמרא Gemara pushes back. ואלא מאי כמטלטלי דמי, ve-ela mai
kemetalteli dami, so what do you want to say? You want to
say that they're like
movables, chattels? מאי אפילו? mai afilu? Why does it say when you
say everything in it, you're even selling the slaves? Just say you're
selling the, you're selling the slaves, you're selling the מטלטלין metaltelin and
the slaves. It sounds like even with the word everything in it,
there's some חידוש chiddush about slaves, okay? Why should there be a
חידוש chiddush if slaves are just simply in the מטלטלין metaltelin category?
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מאי אית לך למימר, ela mai
it lach lemeimar, שאני מטלטלי דניידי ממטלטלי דלא ניידי. shani metalteli de-naydi
mi-metalteli de-lo naydi. מטלטלין metaltelin that, that moved on their own, I
mean all מטלטלין metaltelin is movable by another person, but מטלטלין metaltelin
that are ambulatory from מטלטלין metaltelin that are not ambulatory are slightly
different. So meaning why do you think, let's just take a pause
and stop, stop this whole categorization of מטלטלין metaltelin and קרקע. karka.
Why do you think if I said the town and everything in
it, slaves and animals might not be included?
Because they're, right,
they could walk out!
They're only in it right now, a second from now they could
leave, they could leave on their own accord. They're not held in
it the same way inanimate objects are held within a city. So
the גמרא Gemara says this has nothing to do with whether they're
קרקע karka or מטלטלין. metaltelin. I don't care what category they're in.
They might not be in the words town, they might not even
be in the words town and everything in it because they're ambulatory.
So that's the חידוש, chiddush, it has nothing to do with how
you categorize them as קרקע karka or מטלטלין. metaltelin. No, your kite
doesn't, it doesn't ambulate by itself. Okay,
anyway, okay, אפילו, afilu, so therefore the גמרא Gemara says, דלא נייד
אתא אפילו תימא כמקרקע דמי, delo nayad ata afilu tema kemekarka dami,
even if they're technically קרקע, karka, שאני מקרקע דנייד ממקרקע דלא נייד.
shani mekarka denayad mimekarka delo nayad. This is ambulatory קרקע, karka, so
that's why it wasn't included in the word town, and even when
you say town and everything in it, it's a חידוש chidush that
it's included, because this moves around. So this has nothing to do
with the קרקע karka versus מטלטלין metaltelin question. That was not relevant.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says again, אמר ליה רבינא לרב
אשי, amar leh Ravina le-Rav Ashi, תא שמע, ta shema, come in
here, and now we're going to see why we included it. One
reason we included it might be because we're just talking about a
שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera that says give all my מטלטלין metaltelin to
so-and-so. But another reason is because it ties in to the משנה
Mishnah we read yesterday. So come in here, תא שמע, ta shema,
הכותב כל נכסיו לעבדו יצא בן חורין. hakotev kol nechasav le'avdo, yatza
ben chorin. Somebody says to a slave, all of my, all of
my possessions, property not meaning a land, all of my possessions, all
of my possessions are given to you, so the slave goes free
because the slave is included in possessions. Okay. שייר קרקע כל שהוא,
shayer karka kol shehu, he says, all of my possessions except for
a little bit of land, and he doesn't say which plot of
land, he just says in an abstract way, a little bit of
land, לא יצא בן חורין, lo yatza ben chorin, he doesn't go
free because we're, because that might mean except for you, you're called
קרקע. karka. רבי שמעון אומר לעולם הוא בן חורין עד שיאמר כל
נכסיי נתונים לפלוני עבדי חוץ מאחד מריבוא שבהן. Rabbi Shimon omer: le'olam
hu ben chorin, ad sheyomar kol nechasai netunim li-Ploni avdi chutz me'echad
meribu she-bahen. No, land still means land. Even if slaves has a
הלכתית halachic status of land, they are not land per se. So
if the guy says except for a little bit of land, he's
not excluding his slave. The only time a slave wouldn't go free
is if he said, you get all of my possessions except for
point one percent of them. So since that's very abstract, you know,
it's except for a little bit, I'm not telling you what's included
in that little bit, so the slave might be included in that
little bit. Okay? But if you said except for land, even if
a slave has a legal status of land, you don't mean except
for you, my slave. Okay, you would not refer to him as
land. Okay? So that's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says. But fine,
we'll put רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon aside, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon excuse
me, and we'll talk about the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. The תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says the word land would be, could possibly mean
slave and would be a way of not freeing the slave. Okay,
so there you see a slave is considered land. Now the גמרא
Gemara says, but now here's what's relevant for us, ואמר רב דימי
בר יוסף אמר רב אלעזר, ve-amar Rav Dimi bar Yosef amar Rav
Elazar, and רב דימי בר יוסף Rav Dimi bar Yosef says in
the name of
רב אלעזר, Rav Elazar, עשו מטלטלין שיור אצל עבד ולא עשו מטלטלין
שיור אצל כתובה, asu metaltelin shiyur etzel eved, ve-lo asu metaltelin shiyur
etzel ketubah, that the, it would be the same if you said
except for a little bit of מטלטלין. metaltelin. I am giving you
my slave all of my possessions except for a little bit of
מטלטלין. metaltelin. מטלטלין Metaltelin is a שיור, shiyur, is a leaving aside
regarding the slave the same way קרקע karka is. The same way
when you say except for a little bit of land, you might
be excluding the slave, when you say except for a little bit
of מטלטלין, metaltelin, you might be excluding the slave. So that answers
our question. When a person says the word מטלטלין, metaltelin, it could,
it is assumed
to be including a slave, like that's a category that includes slaves.
Same as it's also קרקע. karka.
And but that's what I was saying before, it's not exclusive. If
a person says קרקע, karka, it also includes slaves. So for שכיב
מרע sh'chiv mera says, I'm giving to Gloria all my קרקע, karka,
she gets the slaves as well. If they say, I'm giving to
Gloria all my מטלטלין, metaltelin, she gets the מטלטלין metaltelin and the
slaves.
Okay, they're sort of like in both categories, which makes a certain
amount of sense because legally they're קרקע, karka, but people might think
of them as מטלטלין. metaltelin.
Okay, and therefore if a person says to the slave, I'm giving
you all of my property except for a little bit of מטלטלין,
metaltelin, unfortunately the slave does not go free because the מטלטלין metaltelin
could, you know, might refer to the slave himself. All right, so
that's one way of resolving it. But now the גמרא Gemara isn't
done. Now what's the last line, that really
did the big question when you give over your slave to somebody
else, he becomes free?
No, it does not come free.
He becomes free from you.
Right, but does, but becomes, but does not become a freeman. Just
the, just the ownership transfers. Right, yeah, exactly. But if you give
him to himself, he becomes free. Right. Okay. So now what's this
ולא עשו מטלטלין שיור אצל כתובה? ve-lo asu metaltelin shiyur etzel ketubah?
So we said that yesterday. That's if a person, a man, is
distributing all of his property to his children, and he gives a
little bit of property to his wife, a little bit of land,
that is considered to be full payment of her כתובה ketubah unless
she objects. You might remember that הלכה. halacha. That is only if
he gives her a little bit of land. If he gives her
a little bit of מטלטלין, metaltelin, it is not considered payment of
the כתובה. ketubah. Why? Because since כתובה ketubah is basically fundamentally to
be collected from the land, especially if he dies, it's going to
be collected from the land and not by the מטלטלין. metaltelin. So
therefore we look at a little bit of land in the context
of distributing all of his property and her non-objection,
objecting, we look at land as a payment of the כתובה ketubah
even if it's only a small amount, but we do not look
at מטלטלין metaltelin that way. So that's what that line meant. מטלטלין
Metaltelin counts like land in the slave case to not free the
slave, but it doesn't count as land in the כתובה ketubah case,
and therefore the
woman... Now, but we're not done. So this right now we seem
to have proven that at least in לשון בני אדם Lashon Bnei
Adam slaves are in the are also in the מטלטלין Metaltelin category.
דאמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן D'amar Lei Rava LeRav Nachman so Rava
said to Rav Nachman מאי טעמא עבדא מטלטלין Mai Ta'ama Avda Metaltelin
מאי טעמא Mai Ta'ama what's the reason that oh so we I
guess we haven't ended the argument. So you see if you say
except for a little מטלטלין Metaltelin the slave doesn't go free. So
Rava said to Rav Nachman here's the reason מאי טעמא Mai Ta'ama
what's the reason עבדא מטלטלין Avda Metaltelin an עבד Eved is included
in the word מטלטלין Metaltelin ומטלטלין למטלטלין הוי שיור U'metaltelin Le'metaltelin Havei
Shiyur and therefore if you're leaving over מטלטלין Metaltelin to מטלטלין Metaltelin
meaning if you're saying the slave who is מטלטלין Metaltelin I'm keeping
a little מטלטלין Metaltelin to myself then you're then you're leaving over
the significant thing. You might be keeping the slave himself to yourself.
Okay וכתובת אשה ממקרקעי הוא U'kesuvas Isha Mi'mikar'kei Hu on the other
hand why by כתובת אשה Kesuvas Isha does מטלטלין Metaltelin not count
like קרקע Karka for this הלכה? Halacha? Because a כתובה Kesuvah is
basically collected from land. So therefore if you give the woman a
little land while he's distributing everything else to the other to his
sons that's considered payment of the כתובה Kesuvah because a classic כתובה
Kesuvah is land. Okay but but because of that if a little
bit of מטלטלין Metaltelin is given to the woman her כתובה Kesuvah
is not seen as being paid off ומטלטלין למקרקעי לא הוי שיור
U'metaltelin Le'mikar'kei Lo Havei Shiyur
but מטלטלין Metaltelin for the sake of something that is basically paid
by land is not seen as a fundamental the language of שיור
Shiyur is a little imprecise here because it doesn't mean like it's
been but it means it's not seen as a fundamental payment is
not seen as representing payment of the כתובה. Kesuvah. So when you
leave over מטלטלין Metaltelin since an עבד Eved might be what you
mean by מטלטלין Metaltelin the slave doesn't go free. But when you
give when the man gives his wife a little bit of מטלטלין
Metaltelin that is not considered payment of the כתובה Kesuvah because a
כתובה Kesuvah is basically paid by קרקע. Karka. Anyway what do you
see? You see that a slave is included in the word מטלטלין.
Metaltelin. That seems to be a good resolution but now we say
on the עמוד ב Amud Beis not necessarily. אמר ליה Amar Lei
Rav Nachman said back to Rava no that's not necessarily what's going
on in that case about the leaving over a little קרקע Karka
leaving over a little מטלטלין. Metaltelin. אנן משום דלא כרות גיטא מתנינן
לה Anan Mishum Delo Karus Gita Matninan Lah we say that that
reason if he says חוץ מקרקע כל שהוא Chutz Mi'karka Kol Shehu
חוץ ממטלטלין כל שהוא Chutz Mi'metaltelin Kol Shehu the reason the slave
does not go free is not because he might be saying I'm
giving you everything except yourself. The reason the slave does not go
free is because the writ does not completely sever the relationship. And
here's an important idea. By a notice by by a woman by
divorce right where the גט Get does not by the way mean
bill of divorce גט Get means basically a שטר Shtar although it
normally means a a bill of divorce. Okay but so here it
says גיטא Gita you might have noticed the word גיטא Gita and
כרות גיטא Karus Gita right like ספר כריתות Sefer Kerisus is like
a bill of severance of divorce. Okay so that's classic words used
by גיטין. Gittin. Why is that? Because we link freeing of a
slave to divorcing of a woman we learn some הלכות Halachos but
conceptually as well those are writs which are not about by the
case of the woman it's not about property ownership it's about status.
A writ of divorce is a instrument which changes the woman's status
from being married to being divorced. Okay it has nothing to do
with property ownership. By a slave it's more complicated because by a
slave this thing which said I am giving you all of my
property was not was fundamentally about property ownership. But by giving the
slave ownership of himself you are effectively freeing him. But that's not
the classic way you free a slave. You know the classic way
you free a slave? You take a piece of paper and you
write הרי אתה בן חורין Harei Atah Ben Chorin and you hand
it to the slave. Okay the same way a man could write
to a woman הרי את מגורשת ממני Harei At Megureshes Mimeni okay
maybe there needs to be a date and some names but whatever
not but not our point right now. You hand it to the
slave. It's not about property ownership it's about status. You are no
longer a married woman you are a free woman. You are no
longer a slave you are a free man. Here is the writ
here is the instrument you are freed. That's called a שטר איסור
Shtar Issur okay as opposed to a שטר ממון Shtar Mamon okay
or קניין איסור Kinyan Issur whatever anyway that effects a status not
an ownership. So here we have a funny thing. When you are
giving slave property ownership of himself okay it's working by transferring property
but to be a writ of manumission that's a fancy word means
freedom okay but to be a writ of manumission it also has
to have the qualities of a גט Get and it has to
have the qualities of a type of a document that changes status.
And part of what that requires because of the comparison to גט
Get is that it has to completely sever the document in itself
has to have no no what's it called no strings attached.
It's actually quite
funny, I think Jenna spoke about this, if you remember when we
did the סיום siyum in the שול shul on גיטין Gittin or
whatever, right? If somebody has a גט get to his wife, throws
a גט get to his wife, and he has a string attached,
literally a string attached, and he can yank it back to himself,
it's not good, because it's not completely severing. There's a physical string
attached. So there could also be a conceptual string attached, right? Let's
say he gives a גט get to his wife and he says,
"You're divorced from me but you're never allowed to go into, you
know, your father's house or my father's house." Since that תנאי tenai
lasts the entire life, the effect of the גט get does not
create complete severance, okay? And therefore it's not כריתותא, kerisuta, and therefore
it's not effective. So here the explanation is, you know why when
it says here's your, here's all the property given to you except
for a little bit of קרקע karka or a little bit of
מטלטלין, metaltelin, you know why it's not effective? Because it's, the גט
get is saying it's, I'm keeping a little bit to myself. And
even though what the guy is keeping to himself is not the
slave himself, it's the prop-, it's some of his property, but since
this is affect-, this שטר shtar has to work not just as
a document to transfer ownership, but as a status change, okay, it
has to be like, you can't still have your claws in it.
So that thing would change the slave's status, that claim "I am
giving you everything, but I don't really mean everything. I'm keeping a
little bit," so that means that there's some holding back in that
language that is freeing the slave. And that is, even though it
doesn't mean the slave himself. Now let's get-, let's transfer it. Let's
say in the same-, let's think of a different case. Let's say
in the same document you said, "I am transferring to you ownership
of yourself, I'm also transferring to you ownership of all of my
property, except I'm keeping my car." Okay, that probably would work, because
the line in the document that frees the slave is absolute. Let's
even have another example. Let's say he said, "I am giving you
all of my property except for my car." That might also work
because the division is clear. You get this, includes yourself, and I
get this. Okay, but in this case, "I'm giving you everything except
for somewhere in this big pile of stuff, which includes you, I
have some ownership," right? Here's the pile of all of my stuff,
you know, you're in that pile, my car's in that pile, now
I'm going to have to draw-, draw a car. Okay, I have
all this stuff in that pile. I'm giving you this whole thing
except for some undefined amount. Even if that undefined amount is clearly
not you, because I'm saying מטלטלין, metaltelin, okay, but since the thing
that freed you was the line that I gave you everything and
now I'm saying "but I'm holding back something," that's seen as not
complete severing the relationship, okay? It's not completely sort of saying and
giving it to you totally. All right, so it's exact-, not always
exactly clear what to define as כריתותא kerisuta or not כריתותא, kerisuta,
but that's the counter-claim. So therefore he's saying it has nothing to
do with the fact that a slave is called מטלטלין. metaltelin. It
has to do with the fact that the language or what's being
done by this document if it's freeing the slave, there's some holding
back that's taking place in this document.
We're explaining רב נחמן's Rav Nachman's response to רבא Rava to say
that don't, yeah, wait, we're explaining why רב דימי Rav Dimi says
that מטלטלין metaltelin is a שיור. shiyur. מטלטלין metaltelin is not necessarily
a שיור shiyur in this because the word מטלטלין metaltelin might mean
the slave. The word מטלטלין metaltelin doesn't mean the slave, but the
word מטלטלין metaltelin means something in this big pile of stuff that
I gave you, I'm keeping for myself, and that means that it's
not a complete severance, okay? So therefore it's a very different reason
why it's not effective and it's not because that slaves are cons-,
might be considered מטלטלין. metaltelin. Okay, so we don't have an answer
to whether when a person says מטלטלין metaltelin in their לשון בני
אדם leshon bnei adam does that include slaves or not. Now we're
going to go on.
Now we're going to like step back and talk about again this
division here of כל נכסיו kol nechasav and מקצת נכסיו. miktzat nechasav.
So אמר ליה, amar lei, so אמר רבא אמר רב נחמן, amar
Rava amar Rav Nachman, so רבא Rava says in the name of
רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, חמישה עד שיכתבו כל נכסיהם. chamisha ad sheyichtevu
kol necheseihem. There are five categories of הלכה halacha where there's a
halachic difference between whether you're giving away all your property or selling
all your property or only some of it. I mean obviously the
difference is are you doing it all or some, but meaning no,
it's a category shift when you decide to do all your property
as opposed to only some.
What are those? So
ואלו הן, ve'eilu hen, these are they: שכיב מרע, shachiv mera, the
person on the deathbed, עבדו, avdo, a case of a slave, אשתו,
ishto, a case of a man's wife, ובניו, uvanav, a case of
his sons, and מברחת, mavrachat, a שטר shtar that is written to
hide property from somebody else. So let's, let's define them now. שכיב
מרע דתנן, shachiv mera detnan,
שכיב מרע shachiv mera is our
משנה. mishna. שכיב מרע שכתב כל נכסיו לאחרים ושייר קרקע כלשהו מתנתו
קיימת. shachiv mera shekatav kol nechasav le'acherim veshayer karka kolshehu matanato kayemet.
If you write away all of your property and then he gets
better, I'm sorry... You write away all but leaves back a little
bit of land, then even if he recovers, the sale is still
binding. It's not in the מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shchiv mera category
because a little bit of land was left over. לא שייר קרקע
כל שהוא, lo shiyar karka kol shehu, if a little bit was
not left over, then it's in the—if everything was given, defined as
no land left over, although we debated before maybe that might also
mean no מטלטלין metaltelin based on that argument earlier, but anyway, but
if everything was given, אין מתנתו קיימת, ein matanaso kayyemes, then it
is the classic law of שכיב מרע, shchiv mera, and if he
gets better, the gift is void. So there is a category difference
between giving all and giving a little bit less than all. That's
the case of שכיב מרע. shchiv mera. עבדו, avdo, the עבד, eved,
what we just said, דתנן, d'tnan, הכותב כל נכסיו לעבדו, hakoitev kol
nechasav l'avdo, somebody writes all his property to his slave, יצא בן
חורין, yatza ben chorin, he goes free. שייר קרקע כל שהוא, shiyar
karka kol shehu, if he says everything except for a little bit
of land, לא יצא בן חורין, lo yatza ben chorin, he doesn't
go free. Okay, so we said two reasons: maybe the little bit
of land means the slave, or maybe it's a problem of כרות
גיטא, kerut gita, it's not complete severance, but either way, there is
a fundamental category difference whether it is all the land or not.
Once it's all the property, the slave goes free. And similarly there
we had a discussion whether that meant only קרקע karka or even
מטלטלין. metaltelin. There too it seemed to be agreed that it means
even מטלטלין. metaltelin. Okay, so there's another case, whether that document frees
the slave or not. Number three: אשתו, ishto, his wife. דאמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל, d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, הכותב כל נכסיו לאשתו,
hakoitev kol nechasav l'ishto, we also mentioned this. A man gives over
all his property to his wife—no, actually we didn't, we mentioned this
much earlier, but not earlier today. A man writes over all of
his property to his wife, לא עשאה אלא אפוטרופא. lo asah ela
apitropas. He does not really want her to have all the property,
he would never completely disinherit his kids, so we're going to read
the fact that he gifted all of his property to his wife
on his deathbed or whenever he did it as a way of
making her the executor of the estate, but not really to own
all the property. You might remember that, right? We did that a
while ago. So there again, that's only all the property. If he
left over a tiny bit for his kids—now, would that mean קרקע?
karka? Would it even mean מטלטלין? metaltelin? Okay, like we're not spelling
that out, but if he left over a little bit for his
kids, then this הלכה halacha would not be applied. If he gave
her 99 percent, she would own 99 percent. As soon as he
gives her 100 percent, she owns nothing. All right. בניו, banav, the
son. דתנן, d'tnan, this is what we just taught, discussed. הכותב כל
נכסיו לבניו, hakoitev kol nechasav l'banav, he's distributing all of his property
to
his kids, וכותב לאשתו קרקע כל שהוא, v'chotev l'ishto karka kol shehu,
אבדה כתובתה. avda kesuvatah. She loses her כתובה kesuvah because that's seen
as the combination of the fact—number one, קרקע, karka, as we said,
is a classic thing that a כתובה kesuvah is paid with. Number
two, she didn't object. And number three, it was in the context
of completely divesting himself of all of his property. So in that
type of a case, it's seen as though she agrees to accept
that as payment for her כתובה. kesuvah. But that's only all the
property. If he distributed 99 percent of the property and gave her
a little bit of land, she would not lose her כתובה, kesuvah,
okay? Because he's leaving aside property for her to collect from, and
once she can collect from the little bit that he's leaving over,
the assumption is she has the liens still that are valid, that
were always valid, and she can even collect from the orphans. All
right, so that הלכה halacha that she's seen as waiving her כתובה
kesuvah rights or accepting it as full payment of her כתובה kesuvah
is only when all the property is distributed, not 99 percent. מברחת,
mavrachas, what's the case of hiding property?
דאמר מר d'amar mar מברחת mavrachas צריכה שתכתוב כל נכסיה. tzerichah shetichtov
kol nechasav. A woman with hiding her property has to write away
all of her property. What does this mean? This
means—it's very interesting that this device was there already in the time
of the גמרא. Gemara. Like what would you do nowadays, right, if
you wanted to protect your property from, like, you know, you were
getting married and you wanted to make sure, like, you know, there
would be ways, right? You'd, like, put it in some type of
a trust or, you know, there's ways you protect your property, right?
So what they would do in the גמרא Gemara would be, a
woman's getting married—it doesn't have to be the case of a woman,
but this is the case—a woman's getting married and she doesn't want
her husband to get his claws into her property. She doesn't want
him to be אוכל oichel the פירות peiros while they're alive, she
doesn't want him to inherit from her if she were to die.
So what she does is, she basically writes, "I am hereby gifting
all of my property to my best friend Cheryl," okay? Or to
my son from my other marriage, whatever John, and whatever she does,
and she writes over that שטר. shtar. So the הלכה halacha is—this
is
fascinating—because it's all of her property, we know she's only doing it
to protect it from her husband. So Cheryl does not own her
property, but she succeeds in protecting it from her husband... like in
a פשיטא. p'shuta. But no, but the question is: who owns the
property? She still owns it because she didn't really want Cheryl to
have it, she just didn't want her husband to have it, so
she still owns it. So you might think if she still owns
it, that means if she's going to die, he's going to inherit
from her, right? You know, or he's going to still get the
אכילת פירות achilas peiros or whatever he's going to get
because—no. But because she's trying to protect it, we actually allow this
to serve as a device to protect it from the husband, right?
Can Cheryl eat the פירות? Peiros? Can
she take apples from the tree and eat them?
Yeah, I think the answer is no, it does not belong to
Cheryl. Now the question is, of course, so if she dies, then
I guess who would get it? I guess it would go on
to her own
heirs, right?
Her biological heirs. Yeah.
Right, the whole point is that what she wants it to be
that vis-a-vis her marriage to this guy, it's like she has no
property. Okay, but she doesn't really want Cheryl to own it. She
just wants it to be, as far as it's concerned me marrying
this guy, I, you know, it's as if it's all given to
Cheryl, as if I have no property. Or a 401k. Whatever it
is, it's fascinating that they created this device, right? You would think
it's like one or the other. Either we say you didn't really
want Cheryl to own it, so you own it, and since you
own it, your husband's going to get whatever, you know, whatever. Or,
Cheryl owns it. But we actually allow her to do exactly what
she was trying to do, which was to protect it from her
husband, but not to give it to Cheryl. Okay, so that's the
story of מברחת. Mavrachas. But that is only if it's all the
property. If she leaves over a little bit, then we don't assume
that that's what she meant by it, we assume she meant the
literal gift. Now, by the way, the רשב"ם Rashbam points out that
there is language you can write in a שטר Shtar that even
if it's not all of it, you can make it clear from
the שטר Shtar that you still mean it to serve as this
sort of protective trust and not really that Cheryl should own it,
okay? So he has a language, I forgot exactly what the language
is. But anyway, so it's not like you really only can only
do it one way and not the other, there's a way to
do it the other way. Let's take a look. Let me see
the language.
מהיום ולכשארצה. Mehayom Velichshe'ertza. If you write basically in it, I am
giving this property to Cheryl as of today, but whenever I want
to, I can void the gift, okay? So some type of a
language like that. He has the whole language? Yeah.
מהיום ולכשארצה, Mehayom Velichshe'ertza, okay? So if you basically sort of that
would be another way to sort of, you know, do it without
giving it all. But if you gave it all, even without any
separate special language, it's understood to basically be like a trust and
not a real gift. So that's another case where we say there's
a difference between all and part. Okay? ובכולהו, Ubechulhu, now in all
of those cases, מטלטלי הוי שיור. Metalteli Havei Shiyur. The same is
true whether it's קרקע Karka or מטלטלין. Metaltelin. We debated that by
our case of שכיב מרע, Shchiv Mera, right? We made the claim
it meant מטלטלין, Metaltelin, but then there was a pushback in the
גמרא. Gemara. Here, right, רבא Rava in the name of רב נחמן
Rav Nachman seems to be siding with those opinions. Was it before
רבא? Rava? No, it was not רבא Rava before. That says that
מטלטלין Metaltelin would also be considered מקצת Mikztas in the case of
שכיב מרע Shchiv Mera and actually it would be considered מקצת Mikztas
in all those cases. Let's go through them again.
שכיב מרע, Shchiv Mera, עבדא, Avda, we said מטלטלין Metaltelin
was a שיור, Shiyur, maybe because of כורסיטא. Kursita. Okay? אשתו, Ishto,
giving the wife all the property, if it's 100 percent, then it's
only an אפוטרופסא, Apotropsa, she's only an executor; 99 percent, it's hers,
and even if the stuff you didn't give her was מטלטלין, Metaltelin,
it would still be a valid sale. So there מטלטלין Metaltelin is
also good. Okay? And this case of מברחת, Mavrachas, even if a
little bit of מטלטלין Metaltelin is left over, it's not considered to
be, it's considered to be a real bill of sale, not a
מברחת. Mavrachas. So the one case מטלטלין Metaltelin doesn't count is ובכולהו,
Ubechulhu,
I'm sorry, I lost my place,
מטלטלי הוי שיור לבר מכתובה, Metalteli Havei Shiyur Levar Miksuva, except in
the case of כתובה, Kesuvah, of the case of distributing all his
property and giving his wife a little bit of land, דמקרקעי תקינו
רבנן, Demekarkei Tikinu Rabbanan, ממיטלטלי לא תקינו רבנן. Mimitalteli Lo Tikinu Rabbanan.
The rabbis said it by קרקע, Karka, not by מטלטלין. Metaltelin. Now,
what do we mean? This is actually a little confusing, okay? And
it was confusing before as well when I was reading it the
way the רשב"ם Rashbam read it, but it could be read a
different way. When we say קרקע Karka is a שיור Shiyur by
כתובה, Kesuvah, okay, what are we talking about? There's two ways we
could be talking about a שיור. Shiyur. Here's the guy, right?
Here's his wife, here's his kids.
Make them smaller,
okay? So he's doing, if he's distributing all his property, right? He
gives each kid a little bit of property,
and he gives his wife, okay, and he gives his wife קרקע
כלשהו, Karka Kolshehu, right?
קרקע כלשהו. Karka Kolshehu. And we say that that equals her כתובה.
Kesuvah. Okay, the הלכה Halacha is that that becomes her כתובה, Kesuvah,
right? Even though it's a tiny amount, that's the point, even though
it's tiny, right? Because it's part of distributing all of his property
to his kids. That's the point. Now before we said that that's
only if he gives her קרקע. Karka. If he gives her מטלטלין,
Metaltelin, since a כתובה Kesuvah is not normally paid by מטלטלין, Metaltelin,
it would not be considered payment by the כתובה. Kesuvah. That's one
way in which we say in this case we only mean קרקע,
Karka, not מטלטלין. Metaltelin. But now and even before, we're talking about
this idea of שיור. Shiyur. Are you giving away everything or not
everything? Right? And what's the difference between
every... Let's say in this case, did all of this, but he
kept for himself like a few bucks. Okay? He didn't, he gave
away 99%. All of this is 99%. Okay. The הלכה halacha would
be, this would not be payment of the כתובה. Kesuvah. This is
only treated as payment of the כתובה Kesuvah when he's giving 100%
distributing of his property. Right? That's the point we're making now. There's
a difference between 100% and 99%. Everybody with me here? Yes?
No,
no. That's when it's 100% to her. Here it's 100% distributed between
the kids and her. Okay, right? So if it was 99% to
the kids and her and 1% to himself, okay,
then it would not be payment of the כתובה. Kesuvah. So now
the parallel discussion is not what is he paying her, is it
קרקע karka or מטלטלין? metaltelin? The parallel discussion to what we've been
discussing before is what is the 1% he's leaving over for himself?
Is that קרקע karka or מטלטלין? metaltelin? Like because that's our question.
When we say it has to be 100%, if you leave over
a little, it's not the same הלכה. halacha. Only when you leave
over a little קרקע karka or even when you leave over a
little מטלטלין? metaltelin? Okay, so it seems like we're shifting now and
we're saying this הלכה halacha that it's considered payment of her כתובה
Kesuvah is only when he left over no קרקע. karka. Because if
he left...
What?
He should at least be saying that.
At least be saying, right. If he left over some קרקע, karka,
okay, it's not payment of the כתובה. Kesuvah. Why? Because if he's
leaving over some קרקע, karka, then she still has the ability to
collect more of her כתובה Kesuvah from the קרקע karka he's not
given to the kids.
One minute, one minute. And once she's still going to have rights
to collect her כתובה Kesuvah from this he's leaving over, we assume
she's also not forfeiting her rights to collect her כתובה Kesuvah from
what he's giving the kids. But if he gives it all away
and she's got nothing left to collect her כתובה Kesuvah from, then
we would assume she's waiving her rights to collect her כתובה Kesuvah
from the kids. Let's say if instead of קרקע karka this was
מטלטלין. metaltelin. I don't know how to draw מטלטלין. metaltelin. We'll draw
my car again. Okay, my bad example of a car. Okay, anyway.
Okay. If he's left over מטלטלין, metaltelin, okay, then we would say
and even though he gave her קרקע. karka. Again, there's two things:
what is the little bit he's giving her and what is the
little bit he's leaving over. Okay, here we'll leave over an apple.
Okay, there. Okay. So he left over a little מטלטלין. metaltelin. In
that case, we would say that that is like 100% has given
over. And it is considered payment of her כתובה. Kesuvah. Why is
a little מטלטלין metaltelin not considered holding back? Because she can't collect
her כתובה Kesuvah from the apple. So since she can't collect her
כתובה Kesuvah from the apple, it's not like he's still holding on
to her כתובה Kesuvah rights. So in all the other thing by
a מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas shichiv mera, you're understanding that even if
he holds over a little bit, one apple, keeps it to himself,
okay, then that would still be not a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas
shichiv mera. That would not be 100%. All these other cases by
an עבד, eved, I'm giving you all my property except for a
tiny bit of מטלטלין, metaltelin, all these cases, holding back מטלטלין metaltelin
is considered to be not 100% where you need 100%. But in
this case, holding back מטלטלין metaltelin is considered to be 100% because
the logic is that the reason it's a difference is is he
leaving back stuff that she can still collect from. And since she
can't collect from the apple, then it is 100% and this does
become payment of the כתובה. Kesuvah. All right? Pretty clear?
Does that change as you were saying when we change the concept
of movables in terms of where she could get her money after
the Gaonim?
Yeah, after the גאונים Geonim it might be different. It might be
different, right. It could be that this הלכה halacha would change as
well. Right. Wait, let me just read that inside. So it says,
ובכולו, uv'chulo, in all these cases, מטלטלי הוי שיור, metalteli havei shiyur,
if he held back a little bit of מטלטלין, metaltelin, it does
not have the הלכה halacha of giving away 100% and these different
הלכות halachos don't apply. לבר מכתובה, L'var mikesuvah, except for כתובה, Kesuvah,
דבמקרקעי תקינו רבנן, d'bimkarkei takinu rabanan, for קרקע karka is where the
rabbis established that he has a right to collect from, במטלטלי לא
תקינו רבנן, bimtalteli lo takinu rabanan, not so מטלטלין. metaltelin. Okay, and
therefore since she doesn't have a right to collect from this apple,
as far as she's concerned he's given away 100% of his property.
And if she's willing to accept this little bit
in that context without objecting, that's payment of the כתובה. Kesuvah. Yes.
Since she's the only one of those five categories that's holding a
kind of bond, she's a
type of creditor, right?
In that sense.
Oh, she's the only one that's about שעבודים, shibudim, right, which is
why we don't make those distinctions in those other cases. Right, that's
accurate. Yes, correct. Okay, אמימר אמר. Amimar amar. Only one of those
five categories is holding a kind of bond, she's a type of
creditor, right? And that's for the כתובה, ktuba, she's the only one.
Right, there's none of these others that are about שיעבודים, shibudim, right,
which is why we don't make those distinctions in those other cases,
right? That's exactly it. Yes, correct. Okay. אמימר אמר, Amemar amar, מטלטלי
דכתבי בכתובה ואיתנהו בעינייהו הוה שיעור. metaltalei dichtivi bichtuva ve'isnhu be'aineiyahu havei
shiur. One minute. Here's a case where there would be a difference.
Let's say, maybe here it is better to talk about a car
because it's a little bit more realistic. Let's say the מטלטלין metaltalin
he's holding back for himself here is the car.
Okay. I'm a bad drawer of cars.
It needs a hood, right. Okay. Anyway, the מטלטלין metaltalin he's leaving
back is his Ferrari, but she always loved this Ferrari. So in
the כתובה, ktuba, it basically says, in the כתובה ktuba it says,
okay, and it says explicitly, here it says באחד בשבת, be'echad beshabas,
okay, blah, blah, blah, and it says here somewhere, the Ferrari. Ferrari.
It says, what? An ע, ayin, Ferrari? Okay. Anyway, so basically says
that you will have liens on the Ferrari. And even after I
die and the kids inherit the Ferrari and whatever, you, although you
don't have a right on any other מטלטלין, metaltalin, you only have
liens on the קרקע, karka, you'll be able to collect your כתובה
ktuba from the Ferrari. Okay. In that case, if he held back
the Ferrari here, it would have the הלכה halacha of holding something
back because the logic is, as long as something is left in
his control that she still has rights to, she's not giving up
her כתובה ktuba rights. So normally she wouldn't have rights to any
מטלטלין, metaltalin, it wouldn't have liens on any מטלטלין, metaltalin, okay? But,
I mean, it would when she could collect it when the guy
was alive, but not when he was dead. But if it's written
explicitly in the כתובה ktuba and she does have liens on it,
that would apply even by the heirs and he's leaving it behind,
then it's not considered 100 percent she's waiving her rights. Okay. So
it says like this.
Okay. אמימר אמר Amemar amar מטלטלי דכתבי בכתובה ואיתנהו בעינייהו הוה שיעור.
metaltalei dichtivi bichtuva ve'isnhu be'aineiyahu havei shiur. If they're written in the
כתובה ktuba and they're still around, that is a שיעור. shiur. It's
not 100 percent. Okay. Now, now we're going to shift gears because
we talked before about, now we're going to talk about a line
between when there's a category difference between 100 percent and 99 percent
and what's considered to be that line. We've discussed what a person
means when they're saying I'm giving my מטלטלין metaltalin to somebody. Now
we're going to discuss a word not מטלטלין, metaltalin, chattel, but a
word נכסים. nechasim. I'm giving my possessions to somebody, my property to
somebody. How all inclusive is that word נכסים? nechasim? This could be
a שכיב מרע, shachiv mera, could be a בריא, bari, but either
way, what does that word mean? So let's take a look. Okay.
אמר נכסי
לפלניא.
Amar
nechasai leplanya. Somebody said, "My נכסים nechasim should go to פלוני." Ploni.
עבדא איקרי נכסי. Avda ikri nechasai. A slave's included in that. Again,
this is just word
"possessions" or property.
דתנן הכותב כל נכסיו לעבדו יצא בן חורין. Detnan hachoteiv kol nechasav
le'avdo yatza ben chorin. If you write your slave, "I'm giving you
all of my נכסים," nechasim, all of my property, he goes free.
Why? Because we say the word "property" means the slave himself. Okay,
so the word נכסים nechasim includes slaves. Good. What else does it
include that we might have a question about? ארעא איקרי נכסי. Ara'a
ikri nechasai. Land. Like, don't say land, נכסים nechasim means like מטלטלין,
metaltalin, it doesn't mean land. No, the word נכסים, nechasim, possessions, includes
land. How do you know? דתנן נכסים שיש להם אחריות נקנין בכסף
ובשטר ובחזקה. Detnan nechasim she'yesh lahem achrayus niknin bechesef uveshtar uvehachzaka. נכסים,
nechasim, property that has liens, meaning land, is acquired through, you know,
money, an act of taking possession, and a שטר, shtar, a writ.
Okay. But anyway, the משנה Mishna refers to them as נכסים שיש
להם אחריות. nechasim she'yesh lahem achrayus. What's, what's, how, what's נכס, neches,
right, in modern Hebrew, what would, how would you translate that? Possession
or property? Somebody's, does anybody know? I'm just gonna guess.
I think possession. Uh
huh. But wait, but it says here נכסים שיש להם אחריות, nechasim
she'yesh lahem achrayus, which is like in the כתובה, ktuba, it's like
קרקע. karka. Right, but, but you can, you can insure other...
Right, but by stand, but the default is that it's קרקע. karka.
Default, yeah, exactly. But we're not excluding מטלטלין, metaltalin, because now we're
going to include מטלטלין. metaltalin. Okay. גלימא איקרי נכסי. Gelima ikri nechasai.
Meaning your shirt, or basically any מטלטלין. metaltalin. דתנן ושאין להם אחריות
אין נקנין אלא במשיכה. Detnan veshe'ein lahem achrayus ein niknin ela bimeshicha.
Things that don't have liens are
acquired through the act of משיכה, meshicha, drawing it out to you.
But anyway, the משנה Mishna uses the word נכסים nechasim to refer
to both. So now we see, משנה Mishna uses the word נכסים
nechasim to refer to slaves, land, and chattel. What else does it
use the word to that might be in a different category? זוזי
איקרי נכסי. Zuzei ikri nechasai. Money, actual cash. Right, you could think
that cash is cash, it's not possessions. Okay. But no, cash is
also, and cash has different ways of taking possession, of taking ownership
over it. Even that is called נכסים. nechasim. How do you know?
דתנן ושאין להם אחריות נקנין עם נכסים שיש להם אחריות. Detnan veshe'ein
lahem achrayus niknin im nechasim she'yesh lahem achrayus. Property that does not
have liens can be possessed through taking possession of land, you can
take possession of other property, בכסף ובשטר ובחזקה. bechesef uveshtar uvehachzaka. If
a person takes possession of land... With כסף שטר חזקה, kesef shtar
chazakah, they can get possession of the other property that the seller
wanted to transfer together with it. Okay? How does that prove it's
talking about קרקע? karka? It doesn't. But that's how it's applied. Okay?
כי הא דרב פפא. ki had de'Rav Pappa. And we know that
this line was applied to a way of transferring cash, like the
story of רב פפא. Rav Pappa. הוו ליה תריסר אלפי זוזי בי
חוזאי, havu lei treisar alfei zuzei bei Chuzai, the house of בי
חוזאי bei Chuzai owed him twelve thousand זוזי. zuzei. אקנינהו ניהליה לרב
שמואל בר אחא akneinhu nihaleh le'Rav Shmuel bar Acha אגב אסיפא דביתיה.
agav asifa de'beiteh. Now רב שמואל בר אחא Rav Shmuel bar Acha
was going to the place of בי חוזאי, bei Chuzai, and he
wanted רב שמואל בר אחא Rav Shmuel bar Acha to take them
to court and to get his money back for him or whatever,
or to go there and demand his money back. Now this basically
is in a context of הרשאה, harsha'ah, power of attorney, because רב
אחא בר—this Rav Acha bar רב שמואל בר אחא, Rav Shmuel bar
Acha, he would knock on the door and he says, "Hi, I'm
here representing—who is it here—רב פפא Rav Pappa and please give me
his loan." And they're going to say, "We're not giving you the
loan because we're going to give it to you and it'll get
lost or whatever and he'll say his loan was never paid up.
What's going to—and why do you have a right to demand it
from us? You're not him. You're just doing a favor. We don't
recognize you." So he has to have standing to demand it, and
he has to also represent him enough so that when they give
it to him, they'll have satisfied their obligation of paying up the
loan. So the way you do this is with a הרשאה, harsha'ah,
which is a power of attorney. But the mechanism of a power
of attorney works the following way: רב פפא Rav Pappa transferred the
money to him. Now he is the actual owner of the money.
That's how it works today too.
That's how a power of attorney works.
Power of attorney, you have to trust the person who's the power
of attorney.
No, but you don't transfer the ownership. If I make you my
power of attorney to—as you know, to retrieve my Ferrari there from
Eli, I haven't—the mechanism isn't I am transferring ownership of the Ferrari
to you. But in הלכה, halacha, what allows you to do that
is I've actually transferred ownership to you now. There's another—there's another clause
in it that prevents you from keeping the Ferrari or the money
for yourself. But the point is you have to do it in
a complicated way. It's not just a straight power of attorney. But
it works through transferring the money. So how did he transfer the
cash to רב שמואל בר אחא? Rav Shmuel bar Acha? How do
you transfer cash if you're not around? You can't do it with
חליפין. chalipin. So he did it with אגב agav by giving him
a little bit of land, the cash came with it. Okay? So
he transferred it to him אגב אסיפא דביתיה agav asifa de'beiteh on
the back of—אגב agav is really what אגב agav means, through, right,
on the back of, you know, the porch of his house.
The סף, saf,
right, the סף, saf, right. So it means he gave him a
little bit of the house, a little bit of land, and with
that he transferred him all of this money. So you see what's
relevant for us, that you can transfer כסף kessef with a קנין
אגב, kinyan agav, which means when the משנה mishnah says נכסים, nechasim,
the word נכס nechas that doesn't have liens is transferred with נכסים
nechasim that have liens, is transferred with land. The word נכסים nechasim
includes cash. Cash can be transferred with land. Okay? And the end
of this story is כי אתא, ki ata, when he came back,
נפק לאפיה עד טבח, nafak la'apeih ad Tavach, he went to the
town of טבח Tavach to greet him. He was so thrilled that
he had managed to get back his funds and retrieve his money.
Okay? So cash is considered נכסים nechasim and it's included in that
phrase in the משנה. mishnah.
He had twelve
thousand—twelve
thousand amount in the previous story about the
convert—Oh, איסור גיורא.
Issur Giyora. He had twelve thousand too.
What was it, twelve thousand זוזי zuzei or twelve thousand דינרי? dinarei?
Oh really? I didn't remember that, איסור גיורא. Issur Giyora. Yeah, and
they were trying to transfer the money.
Let's see, 49A I think.
Oh, you're right, תריסר אלפי
זוזי.
treisar
alfei zuzei. And they transferred cash. From—what's the means to transfer cash?
Yeah, that's an excellent point. Okay, I—okay. Now, שטרא איקרי נכסי? shtar
ikrei nechesei? How about—how about writs? I have writs that all these
people owe me money. Okay? And I'm not—it's not they're holding on
to the cash, it's this abstract idea of a
loan. Am I—when I say I'm giving my נכסים nechasim to someone,
am I also giving them these שטרות, shtarot, these I.O.U.s of debt?
So yes, that's also called נכסים. nechasim. דאמר רב אבא בר יצחק,
de'amar Rav Abba bar Yitzchak, שני שטרות הן. shnei shtarot hen. There
are two שטרות. shtarot. Obviously there are more, but there are two
that allow us to try and compare. אמר זכו בשדה זו לפלוני
וכתבו לו את השטר, amar zachu bi'sdeh zu le'ploni ve'chtivu lo et
ha'shtar, if I say to witnesses, "Take possession of this field for—for
David here and I'm also authorizing you to write a שטר shtar
that I have gifted him the field." חוזר בשטר, chozer ba'shtar,
before they've written the שטר, shtar, I still can retract the שטר
shtar because it hasn't been written yet, so I can retract my
authorization. ואינו חוזר בשדה, ve'eino chozer ba'sadeh, but I can't retract the
gift because they already did a קנין סודר kinyan sudar and that
was effective immediately. So the שטר shtar was indep—was independent of the
gift. So the gift was effective immediately, they did a קנין kinyan
and the שטר shtar I can still retract. If I say על
מנת שתכתבו לו את השטר, al menat she'tichtevu lo et ha'shtar, "Take
possession of this, you know, give me your סודר, sudar, take possession
of the field for David on the condition that you write and
give him a שטר." shtar. So in that case, it's dependent on
the delivery. of the שטר. shtar. And since the שטר shtar hasn't
been written yet, I can retract that authorization. So חוזר בין בשטר
בין בשדה, chozer bein be-shtar bein be-sadeh, I can retract the שטר
shtar and by retracting the שטר, shtar, I can retract the gift
of the field. Okay, so those are two cases of a way
in which a שטר shtar is connected to a field. But here,
here's what we're, why we're saying it, רב חייא בר אבין אמר
רב הונא שלשה שטרות הן. Rav Chiya bar Avin amar Rav Huna
shlosha shtaros hen. There's a third one. תרי הני דאמרן, Trei hanni
de-omran, two, the two types of שטרות shtaros connected to the field
that you mentioned. אידך, Idach, and the third, אם קדם מוכר וכתב
את השטר. im kodem mochar ve-kasav es ha-shtar. Let's say I wanted
to sell my field to David. And I was so eager to
sell it, I wanted to have the bill of sale in my
back pocket. So I went to witnesses and said, I want you
to write a שטר shtar that Dov sold his field to David
and sign it. Now I can authorize you to write the שטר
shtar without David there, because it's hurting me, right? It's not hurting
him. So I now have in my back pocket that שטר shtar
that says that I sold David the field, signed and sealed, just
not delivered. Okay, ששנינו, she-shoninu, like we taught, כותבין שטר למוכר ואף
על פי שאין לוקח עמו. kosvin shtar le-mocher ve-af al pi she-en
loke'ach imo. You can write a שטר shtar for the seller, I'm
the seller, the witnesses can sign it for me, even if the
purchaser is not there. So in that case I have this שטר
shtar of sale in my back pocket to sell the field to
David. Finally David agrees to buy it, and he does, and does
a חזקה chazaka on the field. כיון שהחזיק זה בקרקע, Keivan she-hechzik
zeh be-karka, as soon as he does a חזקה chazaka on the
field, נקנה שטר כל מקום שהוא. nikna shtar kol makom she-hu. Even
if I haven't delivered him the שטר, shtar, he owns the שטר,
shtar, and he can demand it from me.
As of the date in the שטר, shtar, it could be a
week before.
Yeah, so we'd have to worry about that, but it doesn't matter.
Right, that's an interesting question and does it lead to whatever liens
issues, but let's not worry about that right now. From the day
he does the חזקה, chazaka, he owns the שטר. shtar. Now, how
do we know that? That the שטר shtar gets possessed together with
the field? So he says we learn it from the following משנה.
mishna. וזו היא ששנינו נכסים שאין להם אחריות, Ve-zu hi she-shoninu nechasim
she-ein lahem achrayus, and things that don't have אחריות, achrayus, in this
case interpreted to mean not cash, like we said before, but a
שטר, shtar, נקנים עם נכסים שיש להם אחריות, niknim im nechasim she-yesh
lahem achrayus, are possessed when you are taking possession of the land.
The שטר shtar that relates to the land, if it already exists
and is signed, you take possession of it when you take possession
of the land by כסף שטר וחזקה. kessef shtar ve-chazaka. אגב. Agav.
But it's a strange אגב. agav.
It's not on the land.
Well, but besides that, it's that it's not even if I'm not
intending to somehow transfer it to you, but because it is seen
as a package with the land. If I want to transfer you
my apples and they're not on the land, that's like one אגב
agav that I'm just bundling them together, but this is like intimately
connected. But what's relevant for us is that phrase of נכסים שאינם
אחריות, nechasim she-einam achrayus, the different אמוראים amoraim is given the meaning
of, one says it means money and cash and one says it
means a שטר. shtar. So that teaches us that the word נכסים
nechasim is broad enough to include all of those things. So we're
going to continue tomorrow to see other kinds of things that might
that would be included in this broad term of נכסים. nechasim. Okay,
yeah.